junkyard love podcast at what age do we
learn how to have better
conversations at what age do we learn to
have better conversations with ourselves
how are you what what's going on just in
your person life how are you oh well I I
want to thank you so much for having me
because I love the concept of your
podcast and I was like I think this is
down my alley and so it's fun to meet
people who want to share a new idea even
if they don't really know anything about
it so that's really cool um um and my
life has been kind of weird the last um
few few weeks my my beloved mother
passed away just a couple of weeks ago
and she was 102 and uh the mother of 12
children of which I am the 11 and um so
these past few weeks has
been you know not unexpected but
difficult um but it was really helpful
to have uh 10 of the 12 siblings come
together and celebrate her life um and
that was was really she was an amazing
woman you know just just this amazing
person and you know I will miss her
every day but she's in my heart every
day so um and after writing this book I
understand that this process is a
natural process and yet humans imbue it
with their emotion and so you have to
work through this what is a natural
thing as as a human who can think and
make ideas and decide how to deal with
things and so it's been instructive on
two levels for me uh but I I love my mom
and miss her um so but I also accept
that you can accept something and be sad
about it yeah absolutely paradoxically
indeed um okay so what has your been I'm
just curious like how it would work for
me because I'll read all these all these
you know books or listen to these
YouTube things and I'll intellectually
hear like okay you know death is a
process of life and when these these
things will happen for me I will
certainly die as well everyone I ever
love like you can intellectualize those
things and feel prepared but but when
that moment happens you know um what was
that like for you was it did your
preparations uh seem fickle in that
moment or well you know I had um my dad
passed away eight years almost to the
day so and that was um before I had
thought of all these things before I had
come up with this Theory before I did
this thing and that experience was much
more difficult for me
because I even though I understood that
you know what was intellectually
happening there was this sadness that I
had never lost really anybody before so
it was and I I didn't quite know how to
deal with it but I think that was
instructive for writing my book and then
when I I got to my mom who's 102 you
cannot I know you cannot live forever
and my mom was sharp up until the last
minute amazing so so you know I I you
know I was still telling her jokes and
singing and you know one of dad's
favorite songs and you know she was
right there um
but I think the hardest thing and she
did it all her way she got she did it
her way she wanted to die at home she
was she got last right she did all the
things that she was ready for and in
fact she joked she was like why is this
taking so long you know and I'm like Mom
I you know those cells like to live you
know that's what they like to do so you
know but it took she's a very literally
a constitution strong body and it took a
while and my biggest worry was I don't
want her to suffer I don't want her to
hurt and make this hard for her any
harder than it I think it has to be and
I think that was the hardest thing for
me was to figure out with my siblings
what was the proper care with the
hospice people and the nurses what was
the right thing to do so that she for me
it was just I don't want her in pain you
know um but
I have accept I was accepting this
wasn't especially once we saw just over
two months this happened it wasn't like
she'd been sick for a long time she'd
been you know she followed the election
she was you know up and you know the
next day she wanted to know what we were
going to do about things you know and I
was like oh um
so it just went so fast and but she did
it on her terms and I could accept it
but I just my my my line was I can't
deal with her being in
pain but but the but the process
itself um I could accept as the natural
way of how things work yeah yeah yeah it
must be this impossible but you know
kind of beautiful balance of continually
you know feeling the sadness emotions
are happening right but you know what
can I do okay what can't I do exactly
EMS I just I
am when and doubt love her love her
children other children my siblings do
what you can to help be you know just do
be there for whatever is needed to be
done and that's what we did and and
during that time we were all together
and then after that time we all work
together to do all the things that
needed to be done you know the funeral
and contacting family and all that stuff
and that's so we did yeah and that was
the best I could do in the
situation yeah yeah and what more could
you do besides the best you can do
exactly exactly and sometimes you know
nobody's perfect so sometimes screw that
one up but you know we were there we
were a team we made decisions together
and when you didn't they were like H I'm
not going to do it that way it's like
oops sorry you know and we moved on it
was good we we got close yeah oh well
beautiful thing um okay well so now I'm
just I'm just curious you
know you said that when your father
passed away eight years ago you hadn't
written this book yet and no now that
you have as we begin I want to start to
introduce introduce your book slowly to
everybody okay so what what do you mean
like how did writing a book change your
perception on death and losing a family
member losing someone you love what do
you mean by that yeah well it wasn't I
guess I would look at it as not writing
a book but writing down this theory of
how humans work I
think um so when I was 10 I was at
Catholic school but I learned about
Evolution so it's the 60s it was you
know wide open we we didn't have these
divisions that we have now and I from
that moment on I was confused it was
like okay we evolve from these animals
okay I get that I could see the eyes and
the ears that we got we got hands and
feet just like animals I get it we're
alike but but boy have we done different
things so we're different and what I
wanted to know was how we were alike and
how we were different and what that
meant for us living as humans on this
Earth and that actually I just it wasn't
like I was like I have a I'm going to go
on and live this you know ask this
question I'm like it was just in the
back burner all my life and everything
that I learned I was like back there at
some point I was saying does this help
answer this question or does this not
answer this question and you know things
like religion I can see their use I grew
up Catholic but didn't answer the
question for me it didn't and then I
went on and I you know I went to school
and I learned all this stuff but you
know I read a lot of Stephen J gold and
about how animals work and that answered
a lot of questions just like oh how do
animals work oh you can see the
similarities between things you can see
how things evolve it's like okay okay I
get that and then I went to school I
became a I I became an accountant and I
I had an economic background and you
know I'm sitting there listening to the
supply and demand and the prices and
everything and and of course technology
never change assuming technology does
not change I'm like oh well that doesn't
work you know but but I was
like I understand these theories and
they make my logical mind it it makes
sense but this is not how people work so
this is not this is not quite right and
then I read a lot of K's and kan's had
it right he's like people are going to
do what people do so you have to use you
make your economic systems work with
what people are actually going to feel
and think and act on and I was like oh
that was a clue um and then I read a
book in 1993 or four a long time ago uh
by Michael Rothchild and it was called
bionomics and what he did was he
compared economics systems human
economic systems the biological system
and oh the lineup was really really
close and I was like oh he's on the
right track but he ended up saying yep
we all need to compete and or you know
capitalism is the way and I was like oh
that just it just went clunk after all
of these things that were going click
click click click it went clunk so I had
to think about that um and then I worked
you know I raised my family I did all
these things I was busy but this the
wheels kept turning and finally I worked
on a uh political campaign for a um a
frunk facing Congressional Campaign so
it was a I'm I'm a Democrat so it was a
a republican was in office and we were
trying to elect a democrat in a very red
district and it was an offe election
2018 so everybody came in you know Jeff
Merkley from Oregon uh Joe Biden came in
you know all these people came in
campaign for Lauren Underwood she was
our Congress she was the one triying to
get elected and I looked back and I was
like why are everybody why are so many
people interested in this and of course
you have to understand that government
is the coordinating system in your brain
in your body your brain is your
coordinating system it keeps all your 35
trillion cells working together in human
societies government is the coordinating
mechanism right and whoever controls the
government controls the rules that
people are allowed to live by and I was
like ah this is what I missed about
humans I understood competition I
understood collaboration I didn't quite
get the coordination piece all the way
and for some reason it just clicked and
then I was able to put the pieces
together I had to work with them a
little bit but I put the pieces together
and I made a parallel construction of D
you know like a concentric circle of DNA
a cell you know a a body those are the
three major pieces and if you look at it
on the human side it's a human and a a
you know you could do a business like
for for like organs and then a society
is at the top and they're brain I'm
sorry brain in the middle humans and
then a society and those things are
actually parallel and they work very
similarly except for one thing humans
have brains and they can think whereas
animals have DNA instructions that are
much more limited in what they can do
they are they are born with those
instructions and have to follow them
humans are born with no ideas but once
they get the ideas they can do whatever
they want with them and that's the
difference and so when they survive they
look different whereas a human like a a
bird can build a nest but it can't build
a three-story concrete structure in the
tree and save it for his gener
generations to come but we can we can
build houses we can build three story
constructs and all kinds of things we
can also build a tent or we can build a
building humans have the vast ability to
choose what they do and that changes the
world whereas animals are very limited
in how they can change the world we have
this massive impact on how we change the
world yeah well okay so what is the what
do you pose in your book for listeners
what is the difference between us and
animals like why why do we have suddenly
bigger brains why are we given the gift
of thinking um and why don't they think
well they do think but it's at a very
much more limited scale remember the the
brain so the brain and the neural system
their job is to keep all the cells
working together in a body so you know
um whether it's a you know a worm or a
tiger who has 300 trillion cells or us
who have 35 trillion
the brain is the coordinator keeps
everybody working together but in nature
nothing stays the same and evolution
occurs and one of the evolution I mean
always Evolution occurs so brains and
bodies are changing all the time that's
why we have tigers and we don't just
have worms because Evolution changes all
the everything all the time and even
today even though we can't see it
because changes work slowly but things
are changing all the time here and what
happened is the evolution occurred that
was growing brains I mean dolphins have
big brains whales have big brains
octopus have big brains so a brain a
brain growth Evolution has been
occurring all along but what happened
with with Homo sapiens is for some
reason our brains kept growing to the
point where our brains brain mass to
body mass ratio is like weird compared
to everybody else I mean we are just
like weird but when we started using
those those extra brain cells to think
and create ideas which is something
animals do maybe on a very limited basis
they don't have big enough brains to do
it but when they evolv and we survived
well doing that it became a Le
evolutionary advantage that continued to
grow yeah so homo sapiens came along
200,000 years ago we only started to
speak and write maybe 10,000 years ago
yeah so the brain was growing all that
time and if you look at apes and you see
what they're doing they can some of them
can use their they can make simple tools
they can but their brains are much
smaller but someplace along the line we
kept using that advantage to grow the
brains to the point where we could
create a new create ideas and act on
them in a way that nobody else could and
that's what I call the idea sphere it's
a a brand new ecosystem based on ideas
it doesn't have any physical
representation except when you put it
into action like when I had the idea of
the IDE of spere and I wrote a book I
put it into a physical form that can
live beyond me I can die tomorrow and
the book hopefully will stay out there
you know it's got a life of its own now
yeah and just like beings in the in the
natural ecosystem these ideas have
created I used Charles Darwin's ideas
from 1859 to write my book in in
2024 those those ideas get to live ju
and evolve just
like just like other beings in the
ecosystem yeah yeah yeah uh somewh in
your book you said something about uh
I'm going to probably butcher you said
it more elegantly but basically the Mind
does not exist with with inside the
brain like our mind is not inside our
head here oh right right well I I make a
distinction between the physical and the
non-physical that what I call our brain
is our physical brain our synapses our
loes they do all this thing but the mind
is the accumulation of the ideas that
that we create from the brain
interacting with its own cells right our
synapses go along and we say ah I need
coffee today that's an idea that you
came up with the brain if you cut open
your head and look for the coffee idea
you wouldn't find it it doesn't exist we
have this ability that no other animal
has quite the way we do to be able to
take these synapses and turn them into a
non-physical idea that we can act on and
then make a physical thing I actually
can think about a cup of coffee and get
a cup of coffee if I just think about a
cup of coffee and don't ever get one
well it's just an idea yeah right but if
I think about the cup of coffee and then
make the coffee oh now I have the idea
and a thing resulting from the idea that
can be shared or at least the has to be
washed or something but you know there's
it's in the physical world though yeah
yeah it's like the precursor to an
action you know and then somewhere in
there we have the ability to to say yes
or no and and make the no act can occur
unless there was an idea before it none
no action you know so oh yeah it's so
fascinating um okay so what I I want to
we don't have to go off this whole
Adventure but I just want to back up a
little bit where do you sit where do you
sit on that jump from apes to humans
like how do we suddenly get a bigger
brain do you think it is like you I've
heard the stone date theory is enticing
to me in some ways um we started eating
and and cooking meat that that sort of
thing where do you land on how our
brains got big yeah I um you know this
is where the fallacy of my book is I
went across and I didn't go down I mean
my first reaction is I don't care it
happened you know what I mean and and
unfortunately because I'm at the top and
I say this happened I know this happened
how it happened oh yeah there's a lot of
great scientists who delve deeply into
these things who know these things all I
know is that it could be a combination
of things there's always the pressures
of evolution the environment is pressing
on people there are are are on these on
Apes there's W you know the weather and
you know they might have to move around
for food where food availability like
you said cooking I've heard that that
has released the energy so that humans
could get more of the protein easier in
their body yep maybe that's true but
what I what I do know it could be
radiation you know the world is full of
radiation you could have just mutated to
the place where you know a couple of
Offspring had these big brains that then
they did so much better you know that
that everybody else kind of you know
that that kind of won the war because
that's exactly how DNA formed before
when DNA was forming back for billion
years ago there was RNA which is still
exists today but scientists think there
were other things there were other
nucleic acids running around but when
DNA got the ability to protect itself
and copy itself and get resources from
the outside it won I mean just it just
cleaned the floor with everybody else
and the only one that existed and stays
still exists today is RNA and DNA uses
RNA to do its work because RNA is the
only thing that can copy stuff DNA
cannot DNA is not capable of copying
stuff but RNA can so RNA got captured
you know and is used in a is exists in a
Cell but only to do the DNA's bidding
all the other nucleic acids gone and my
guess is that's very that's happened
Timeless you know many countless times
in our history that one form of animal
just cleaned up and the other ones we
don't even know about them are gone yeah
you know and that so that's probably
what happened is somewhere along the way
these these larger brain things had such
an advantage that the other ones died
out out we may not have the fossils to
see them but you can you can
surmise the the the path and the journey
even without knowing that that's exactly
what the journey entailed now scientists
can't say that I can't because I'm not a
scientist I can say oh I could surise if
this happen scientist is why I can't
prove it and I'm like you're right
that's why I'm not a scientist yeah yeah
yeah well I mean I think they they kind
of get caught up in the the same exact
conversation with the Big Bang Theory is
like you know you kind of have to assume
that yes it did happen maybe you don't
know all the details it does seem like
we're details out you know like I hear
more and more people on podcast and I'm
like wow that's a mindblowing thing that
totally makes sense and we are
discovering more but you know in order
to do what's next and make action into
our physical reality we have to just at
least let's assume it happened we're
working on figuring out exactly you know
like you said maybe it doesn't even
matter in a sense but like let's asse it
happen so we can make some momentum
forward right right yeah I've been
reading all this about maybe there was a
second big bang with dark matter I'm
like yep it occurs but we uh you know
right now 6% of our universe is physical
matter and the 94% is dark energy and
dark matter I'm like I can't access the
90 the 94% I just can't I have no
ability it exists it's there it it
influences gravitationally you can see
but other than that I just need to know
I'm part of the six% and that's what I'm
working with because I don't know the
rest but my pay grade you know like yeah
yeah it's fun to contemplate on a
Saturday night but like on Monday you
got to go work so exactly exactly so and
that I think that was the hardest part
of the book was figuring
out what I can safely surmise and what I
what I have to um you where I have to
cut that line and say I don't want to go
to deep I I talk a lot about DNA and RNA
but this is where when people say oh
that's so complicated I say look my
102-year-old mother read this book and
she had no problem with it so you can do
it too yeah no absolutely you broke down
very well multiple times I I feel like
you're very good at presenting something
in a paragraph and then your last
sentence or last two sentences wrap it
up very nicely because you have a sense
of humor about you and so my my my
learning style really uh fits well with
the way that you write so wanted to make
it accessible I knew some of these
Concepts just by looking at DNA people
go you know and I not that hard I will
tell you and every time later in the
book when I compare it to humans I will
always
restate what the the natural world was
and this is how humans are different and
so you can see them side by side and
that was very important for me to get
people to be able to see the difference
between humans and animals even as we're
looking at their
similarities yeah yeah okay um so let's
we presented a couple of the cool ideas
in in your book but let's just uh meta
backup just a hair um give me the like I
just sat next to you on an airplane and
I look over your screen and see that
you're like working on a book you're
typing it up and I lean over I say hey
I'm sorry I've been EES dropping I've
been reading a couple of your your
sentences there it looks really
fascinating what are you working on what
are you trying to
present there's your impossible question
to answer like what like say first of
all I say are you a producer would you
like to make a film of
this just teasy um that's always been my
dream somebody will say stubing you yeah
and I'm like H not so easy I have to go
I have to do this the hard way but I
would say that um I've had very hard
time trying to answer this question
because the the answer is simple but the
the case it takes a lot to make the case
to to convince you it's right so I I you
know I would say well I'm writing a book
about how humans fit in the world and
people go H that doesn't mean anything
to you and so it's very hard uh to to
make something sound interesting when
it's like basically what I've come up
with is an idea with all the facts we
still have today I haven't changed any
obviously I haven't discovered any new
facts but I've synthesize them in a new
way
and um people are today don't think that
you can create a new idea you know
everybody's invented everything right
it's like there's so many people there's
so many new ideas and to me I look at
this idea and I say why didn't anybody
think of this before because it seems
really obvious to me but but it's only
obvious because I went through this
journey of looking at how animals work
how people work and and and looked at
the difference I mean literally item by
item where I could um
and really what's happened is in our
world we have had thousands of years of
people theorizing why we exist we have
philosophers we have religion we have
all these people who say this is The
Human Condition this is what we're made
of this is all the and these ideas have
been carrying on for thousands of years
right and then when did we learn about
cells when did we learn about DNA maybe
a hundred years ago so what's happened
is we have all of these answers that
have moved through time and now we look
back and go oh but now we know really
how animals work and we can look at how
cells collaborate and we can make the
parallel to humans but we have to make
some adjustments because of that human
thinking thing but only now can we look
at the parallels and yet nobody has done
it and so I'm not the best messenger for
this I'm a total introvert I you know
but I it's like this is something I need
to tell the world about and let them let
these really smart people go with this
idea so and and what I what I ended with
is that there is in
fact like animals have one job their
cells do one thing they survive and they
have a very intricate way they work
together to survive and I think that
humans also have a
one one sentence solution or a one-word
solution it's two words actually because
we have two levels we have physical
level and we have a a mental level but
we have two words that can keep us
surviving and what I did was come down
to in my case it's one sentence this is
the sentence we need to survive but to
know how to implement that one sentence
we have to look back and look at how
animals do it as a guide so you want to
know the one sentence yes okay the one
sentence is is that humans should be
able to do whatever they want as long as
they don't harm one
another that's it that's exactly how
cells work in a body those cells can do
their jobs 247 but they can't harm the
other cells and if they do the brain
gets not you know gets notice of it and
comes down and says okay we're going to
fix this we're going to stop this they
will do whatever they can to stop harm
to the body and other
cells and they will if in cancer is a
case where the cells trick the brain
into thinking they're part of the body
when they're not and that will kill the
body you know that's a a cancer is a
great example of the cells that got away
with it right yeah but if we you know a
lot of people say love one another
Love's the answer love isn't the answer
we don't we're too different to for
everybody to love and agree with each
other that's okay we are made to be
different we are made to choose but what
we can't do is harm each other and the
coordinating system the government of
humans should be a system that allows
people to maximize their choice and
minimize the harm to others and just
imagine how good our society would be if
we allowed that to be the foundation of
our
decision yeah and when we look at that
our Constitution I think was trying to
do that they just didn't state it so
clearly but those five you know preserve
the Commonwealth uh or preserve the
common good um uh you know protect our
borders do all these things uh you know
keep maximize Liberty I mean we were
doing those things and the so what
happens is the Constitution is like the
set of DNA right for our society and the
laws we
make our are the instruction we the RNA
makes up right we say here's our goal
and the laws need to make those those
things but because we've done it using
religion as our background or or other
philosophical you know ideas we've come
up with ways that don't quite match with
what I call the prime directive you know
the the sort of Do no harm and let
everybody do what they want so if you
were going to make laws uh we would look
at a law and say or look at a thing like
somebody says I don't like gay people I
don't want people to be gay it's like
well gay people don't harm any money
they can marry another gay person and it
does not harm me nothing harms me there
and so the government says nope they get
to do what they want they're not harming
anybody but if the same person says oh I
want 30 guns and I want to be able to
shoot you know kids up in a school we
say oh wait guns can harm people we need
regulations to prevent harm so if you
look at how a government would be
designed in what I call the ideal sphere
we would have a government that assesses
everything based on harm if something
can harm another person it gets
regulated end of story and in a world
where more complicated ideas are coming
up more harm could be done there are
going to be more regulations but the
goal is you can't harm people and you
know things that aren't harmful like
transgender people they don't harm
anybody else no that's okay you know
racism stupid sales sales don't care
about race they don't care if a cell is
a little different of color it means
nothing to them and we should be the
same uh but we have a long cultural
religious philosophical history to do
things differently and we knew when we
think they're right and I'm just saying
look at nature as your guy and maybe
that's not so right yeah yeah yeah well
yeah it's so interesting to think of um
I think the the intersection of like DNA
wanting to proliferate like life wanting
to continue on having um an innate moral
feature to it like is is always a
fascinating intersection um like I feel
like you you know your work in the book
kind of does present ways in which it's
like there's a like nature rewards
morality like um like there there's a
reason why we have these concepts of
like good and bad or we should do the
things and and they have their own
reoccurring uh Rewards well I I make a
point in my book that morality is a
human construct nature doesn't have
morality nature follows instructions and
if the instructions allow it to survive
and its progeny to survive then that's a
good thing to do if it turns out that
it's also good for something that's kind
of an incidental purpose their prime
directive is to survive and they will do
what they can to survive and even
animals who you know they generally will
not attack their own kind because it's
too risky it's the size same size same
way you don't have a good chance it is
much better to go go after the rabbit or
the squirrel who are smaller and can't
defend themselves than to go after a big
animal you know so what looks like
morality is just what worked for
billions of years in survival but we
come along and this is where humans are
really different is we can choose
morality everybody chooses morality so
that's why you have religions with one
set of rules and another religion with
another set of rules and one goes wait
that's not good and we say well it's not
one or the other is Right humans have
the ability to choose our ideas as long
as you get people to accept your idea
it's going to live in the world if
nobody accepts your idea it's not going
to live in the world so you can have a
good idea you can have a bad idea you
can have an indifferent idea but if
somebody follows you that idea starts to
get legs
and that's what history is made of ideas
that won yeah right exactly okay so so
what's your what's your um thought have
you read oh gez I forget the author
Katherine it's called Big magic it's a
no I have not read that oh man I I'm
spacing the author but it's kind of like
a book for creatives and artists like I
it stumbled upon um a friend suggested
it to me kind of like uh it's it's a
good for artists to read of like
believing in yourself type thing like
ideas okay kind of talks about the Muse
a bit um but she she talks about kind of
like where where do ideas even come from
what are ideas um and then she has these
fascinating story she she has one I'll
summarize really quickly of uh she met
this woman and they became close friends
and they're both authors and uh she
ended up this author who wrote This
original book she had this like idea
she'd been kind of working on throughout
the couple years and she has these
characters and a plot line and all these
things um and she kind of shelf it it
was like you know in a storage unit it
was been five years since she had opened
it or something like that well her and
this other author friend came close and
they were having lunch one day and uh
her friend was like well let me tell you
about my new book she starts explaining
explaining it to her and it's this the
correlation she's pretty much telling
her of her own book and she's going like
wait hold on like are you sure are you
messing with me like you didn't read my
book I I didn't tell you about this
whatever and so she kind of backs up and
and kind of expands that you know ideas
aren't our in in in some sense they're
like sometimes if you don't catch it if
you don't take action it's going to go
on to the next person and they might
have that invitation right and it's in
the air in fact there's a very a very
famous story about Charles Darwin so
Charles Darwin did the voids of the
beagle when he was like 22 to 27 he went
on a five-year cruise and he was the the
basically he was the the botanist but he
was also the companion to the captain
because the captain wasn't allowed to
talk to the the lower rungs of the ship
the guys who you know ored the ship so
he needed somebody of his same class to
go with him and keep him from going
crazy that was the whole idea why
Charles Darwin got this five-year gig
and in that if you read The Voyage of
the beagle where he wrote all his notes
you can see that he worked out the
evolution the the the whole concept of
evolution then and then he wrote it and
rewrote it and studied it and did this
and he he put together the book and then
sat on it
until I don't know he had it I think
done in the
1850s and then same idea he gets one uh
from a a guy named Alfred Russell
Wallace something like that sends him
he's over in Tahiti or the the fares and
he sends him his book and says I'd like
you to look at my book and comment on it
before I publish it it's the theory of
evolution and he's like oh and so
but being the kind of man he was they
both agreed
to publish together so if you look at
the front of Charles Darwin book it will
have Wallace's name in the book because
it was like they he didn't publish it
before so they agreed to publish it
together Charles Daren of course got the
most he was more famous than the other
guy so he got all the credit but this in
fact in there's a book I I wrote a a a
fictional story of of this Theory it's
called Dena and in in here the the
character's name is Sarah Wallace and
Wallace is a shout out to Wallace nice
from yeah yeah that was my one Easter
egg I put in yeah yeah little hint but
yeah it's in the air and that's what
they say when you get new theories
they're in the air um I haven't seen
this one as much I think because most
people deal with such details about
humans I'm going what is the foundation
of humans so it's not in there like I I
kind of thought it would be and I would
find people who were connecting to this
I'm not finding that but I'm hoping that
this will be a kind of the book that
people can use to I I think to people to
take this concept of Do no harm and let
people maximize their choice and apply
it to our problems to our Industries to
our to our you know construction of
government all of things and make better
and different decisions that will allow
us to survive yeah okay so how do you
how do you think about like getting this
book in the hands of people who um you
know aren't necessarily interested in
deeply in science or philosophy um or or
even like say they're materialistic
thinkers without realizing they're
materialistic maybe that's not even a
word in their vocabulary you know CU
sometimes a lot of these Concepts uh to
someone who's not used to you know
hanging out in them it takes it's like a
little a little bit you do do a nice job
of setting that layer and building on
top of it though I right right well
that's the first thing you do is you
make it accessible to anybody who is
remotely interested you'd be like oh
here's a way that you can access these
ideas and this might be the kind of a
thing because it's sort of A New Concept
you know you have to revisit things
multiple times before you get them you
know I mean that's why you have you know
12 years of math when you're in school
because you keep repeating the lessons
and then extending it well that's the
one thing the second thing is is you
know I you know social media I'm I'm
doing podcasts I'm I'm gonna sign up to
i' I'd like to do some speaking you know
at different or you know functions where
people can be like oh you know because
what I want is I don't want to own the
idea I want to spread the idea I want
people to take this one simple idea and
look at their world in this vein and see
if they can't come up with better
Solutions um and it sounds easy but it's
not
really it hasn't been something we've
done you know the closest thing we have
is the Golden Rule and that says you
know treat others like you want to be
treated and there's a big caveat in
there it's like well I treat myself like
so I can treat everyone like
like well no that's not what we meant
yeah so you know so this is trying to be
a little more clear you know and how we
do it but I you know it's just it's
going to be a slow uh slow effort
because um it's a big world with lots of
com com uh competing I think just it's
competing ideas uh and and I'm not
talking like I'm competing with Charles
Darwin or Isaac azmo I'm competing with
Kim Kardashian
and tip my tongue yeah yeah it was like
oh yeah you know what's she wearing
today versus oh let's talk about the you
know the definition of human you know
existence it's like H I think I'll go
with Kim you're like I got a lot going
on today like I got yeah exactly exactly
so I know I know what it's like you know
I know what I have to do and I will I
will do it in good faith but I don't
know the answer to how it's going to
turn out I would just hope that people
will pick it up and go oh yeah this is
really worth thinking about um you know
and I'm like okay maybe I should make an
Audi book because young kids don't even
read you know and I'm like okay I'll
I'll I'll do that because like you said
then I can IM imbue my voice with all
the you know the jokes that I want to
get in there that are kind of subtle in
there it's like yeah I can put those in
there yeah yeah as much as I I love
reading in any form I I must say uh I
spend a lot of my time reading audio
books just because I if I can go for a
walk while I'm reading I am having the
best day ever so exactly and and I know
that and that that's like okay this is
the next thing you know um to to find a
a prod I do a YouTube where I've gotten
better at my voice and doing that stuff
and I I am doing you know a three or
five minute you know snippet of the book
great it goes forward but it will you
know at this rate 500 years I'll have it
done you know it'll be good so yeah yeah
yeah well I mean that's I mean I think
that's the fascinating thing about you
know we're talking about even you know
where ideas come from even kind of I'm
thinking of your uh when you talked
about you know bees collecting pollen
you know maybe that bee feels like an
individual or whatever but realistically
they're making honey with with the hive
I think uh in some sense when we follow
our own Bliss or we follow our own like
you know whatever is hinting at us
personally to work on and we put it into
the bigger picture it's like we may not
you know we're we let go of it so it
doesn't have to be so personal anymore
and now it's it can be part of making
honey and part of the pollination
process so right well it's it's very I
think bees are very interesting because
I think I make a book a point in in Dena
in this book that you know there's a
Socratic dialogue going along between
Dena and Sarah Wallace the the main
character and and Sarah asks Dena um
will humans ever be like bees and live
in colonies and Dena says no and and she
says well why not and it's because we
have ideas we went a different direction
once you have ideas choosing and being
individual becomes our nature and bees
follow instructions you have a colony
which is a very weird thing because it's
a it's a structure of its own you can
think of it as its own body where the
queen is the brain and the bees are all
the cells but they're not cells they're
bees but they work together for the good
of the hive and the bean be co uh the
queen bee coordinates them and then that
how they work but we don't work that way
we went the ideal route and so we part
of our meaning is that well let me go
back a little bit is
remember um any animal they have their
DNA is their their sort of goal and when
they process the DNA instructions that's
their rules that they live by right you
know so that's how it works we go along
we are born with no ideas we are
required to create our own goals if we
are going to have a happy life and you
know what's one that's very interesting
is when we're born a lot of times your
parents who are the coordinating
function of your family right they're
the coordinators of your family um they
put ideas in your head but do they
always put the idea in your head that
you must create your own
goals no they're like you need to do
this and you need to do this and you
need to do this they do all the rules
but the kid doesn't have the goals the
kid's confused I grew up and I think
this is part of the roles of you know I
grew up very one of 12 kids where it
wasn't just my mom and dad saying these
are the rules all my older siblings were
saying here's what you do here's what
you do I'm like I'm confused but you
know my job and the job as an adult is
to sort it all out and say these are my
goals these are my values this is what
I'm going to do and then make the rules
that you're going to live by this is not
universally taught to our children yeah
and I think the world would be better if
we taught them that instead of saying
you can't be gay you can't do this you
have to go to church you have to that
it's like the kids like but I'm not
built this way yeah and instead of
saying oh honey you're built this way I
I remember telling my kids you know and
I wasn't very good at it but I said look
you get to be the expert on you you are
your expert and when you're 18 all I
done is put in the best ideas I could
for you but you need to figure them out
which ones work for you and you know my
kids I had three kids and they're
diametrically opposite from each other
not just by nature but because of the
choices and the values that they carry
forward um and I was pretty bad on it
because I was one of those you have to
do this and this and this and this while
I was telling them they get to be the
expert on themselves so course yeah you
know this pretty you know double message
there mixed messages from Mom but yeah
yeah I I think that's just just part of
life is is of course we're going to have
a structure of how we think it should
all work but we're also humans with
emotions and you know the dishes still
get dirty and the burrito still
delicious and all that sort of stuff
right but if we did more to say look you
are a person who has to form your own
goals I can give you lots of ideas is
but know that you form them and it's
okay for you to form the ones that work
for you and form the rules the only the
only rule that exists is you can't hurt
anybody else so whatever goals you form
you just can't hurt anybody else but you
can do whatever you want and I think
that's why my kids are so different from
each other they made different choices
based on what was important to them yeah
yeah wow yeah I mean like what what a
beautiful invitation to open you know to
infinite possibilities you know cuz we
all we all know how the internal
dialogue in our head goes
easyly it can be defeating and so I love
that I think
that's yeah and it made my life better
because as soon as I figured this out I
can look at my own behavior and go you
know okay I didn't hurt anybody by that
and maybe I wasn't really thrilled with
that behavior don't do that again but
you're aren't hurting anybody you're
okay or when somebody's bugging me I go
you know they're not hurting anybody by
that that's just who they are that's
okay you need to step back and be okay
with this because they're not hurting
anybody and it really helps me to sort
out what's really important and what's
not you know and my life is a lot more
peaceful because of that you know and I
think that if we taught kids because
kids are born with I mean babies are
born with literally no ideas and I have
a kind of a funny little story about you
know babies born with no ideas and what
the parents immediately get the baby
home and they start putting ideas in
their heads you know um but if we did a
better job as all these coordinating
functions understanding that they don't
have any ideas and what ideas we put in
their head is very important that that
would be something that if you taught
kids this in school and at home how much
better would they be when they got to 18
and were on their own or started Living
their own life I think we would be
better if we said yeah this is okay you
get you get to make your choices and the
only time the direction occurs is when
you say look you can't harm I'm sorry
you may be uh not like what Johnny did
but you can't hit Johnny you can't you
know that's harm that crosses the line
you can tell Johnny you don't like what
he says in a nice voice that's okay but
you can't you can't haul off and hit him
yeah you know yeah I love this um okay
so I I was thinking um I I'm pretty
fascinating myself in my own world um
I'm deeply into meditation and like I
love learning about the concepts of self
and um I take a I take a lot from like
ADV Vidant I don't know if you're
familiar with those well not much but
some yeah yeah enough to kind of if I
say say the word you know at least a bit
what I'm talking about um so I I kind of
Wonder you just said a baby is born with
no ideas um with the preemptive that I
just was talking about the self and our
identity can you expand a little bit
more on that well yeah now a baby is
born with no ideas which means the the
um the mental structures in their head
right but they're born with all of their
natural instructions they are an uh they
are a person I I I liken a baby to a
full member of the ecosystem and a
potential member of the ideas sphere oh
I love this right they have no ideas but
they have all their instructions so they
have all their history their genetic
history they have inclinations they have
potential talents and you know all those
things are in there but they're they're
they're not uh evident at any point
right you just you have a baby and they
come home and what do they do they cry
and they eat and they poop you know and
that's about it
but you know you start it's it's even
three or four weeks before they start to
smile right you know and they get up in
the middle of the night it's like they
don't know they just they're doing their
full ecosystem members who are surviving
in the way they know how which is cry to
get fed cry when they poop cry when
they're tired cry when anything that's
what they do and then but over time you
start talking to them you hug them they
do all these things and you start
developing ideas even though their
brains can't handle ideas you're putting
ideas in their heads from the very
beginning and they are started to become
members of the idea sphere and what
ideas you put in their heads will be
critical to how they um how they develop
and and the who they are I mean if you
you know are in a in a home in which the
parents are always yelling that child
may be traumatized by that and you won't
even know it for years because they
don't know it's just gotten into their
deep deep deep level of ideas that they
don't even know they had I mean that's
what I think I think by the time I had
my first idea I can remember my fourth
birthday I heard there's already a lot
of stuff that I had figured out that I
didn't know until like my brain caught
up to me to go oh oh yeah I get or I get
this you know so yeah yeah yeah it's a
mystery yeah the ideas are always
working underneath the surface and like
waiting for connections to be made to
where you can express them and the
deeper they are the harder they are to
access and change so that if you have
deep Trauma from early
childhood and you may be acting out here
getting back to that to change it is
really hard um that's why people do
meditation or they go to therapy or they
do these things because these things are
deep and I don't know the mechanisms by
which you can access them to get a child
you know uh to get adult to be okay with
themselves because they didn't learn it
as a child you know that's a hard one
that's a really hard one but that's why
I think it's so important to add the
element of teaching children this sort
of prime directive as they grow and how
it looks in the world at you know when
you're three and four it means you know
you can't take a toy away from your
other friend or you know but you know
but when you're 12 it's going to be like
whoa you can't you know I don't know
drive you know drink and drive the car
home you know I mean there are things
you do the these are potential dangers
and so how you teach that as a child
develops need some experts to help with
people who understand Child Development
and people who understand that's not me
I can give you the idea but I need those
experts to say o this is how we should
Implement these ideas as children grow
yeah yeah well I think about a lot um
just kind of the concept of podcasts in
general or even just you know the
internet social media where connected we
can have you can have an idea um you
know wherever you're at and then within
minutes I can be thinking about the same
idea CU you called me up that's pretty
profound as far as ideas are concerned
like they just streamlined they just
learned how to teleport basically um so
how do you think about um kind of the
way that within time and technology in
all of our cultural advancements how do
you think about um uh I suppose like the
how quickly I
pass through each other and their um
scenarios and settings like is are we
going to look back and look at podcasts
and go wow those were a much more
profound thing than we thought they were
at the time we thought they were just
fun cool conversations weren't talking
about our book but they're actually
we're figuring out what who and what we
are in some ways in a lot of these
conversations is right well I have um I
don't know if you've got to appendix two
of my book but I talk about social media
and okay I didn't get to that I want to
hear that's okay so it' be really
interesting I I'll I'll kind of spoil it
for you a little bit but but um but it's
also any sort of podcasting so the the
the whole concept of social media has
changed how we communicate you know if
you look at the concept of freedom of
speech and you look at how when when
that that was written into the Bill of
Rights um people could speak it was
pretty limited right people could get on
a soap box and speak and it would go
maybe 30 yards and that was it right so
freedom of speech was relatively
harmless um and maybe we had a newspaper
and at the head of the newspaper was was
sort of a you know the newspaper's like
a a gate right and the people at the
head of the newspaper could decide what
goes in and what doesn't go in and what
happened I think kind of historically I
look at it this way is there became a
sort of a mutual benefit there people
wanted truth
so they paid for truth and the new
newspaper people wanted to sell their
newspapers so if they were true people
would buy their newspapers if they were
false and they found out people wouldn't
buy their newspapers because they
couldn't count on them so journalism
grew up with an ethic of we got to tell
the truth it has to be verified we have
to be accountable you know all of these
things there's five values if you look
up journalism there's five values that
they have that says okay we'll do this
and and that worked for a while because
there were the G Gates there were very
limited Gates it was really expensive to
produce a newspaper and and there wasn't
anything else but then you know we got
to radio and um and you know with radio
now we were going over the airwaves and
so they they you know the government
said oh we have a problem now we we we
we can't ensure this truth now so they
put in the fairness Doctrine and the
fairness Doctrine said if you're going
to talk about a current issue you have
to talk about both sides of the current
issue end of story and that um went up
until 1987 when Ronald Reagan abandoned
that law and partly he was sort of like
well we we now had cable TV well cable
TV went under the ground so it couldn't
be regulated over the air because it
didn't go over the air so people could
say what they wanted so it was kind of
like it was coming anyway but so that's
how that's how things have kind of
evolved and now we have social media and
social media the difference is again
it's like now we have anybody can speak
and anybody can say anything they can
post anything the problem
is um there's no longer a standard of
Journalism and the the post that you
make is a physical thing it has a life
of its own yeah it's not it's like a
newspaper you can pass a newspaper
around well you can pass social media
posts around a long time so now it's not
just an idea it's a thing yeah so now is
it really speak when you create a thing
or is it something else and so what I'm
thinking is that freedom of thought I
know I'm I'm blowing your brain I'm
sorry I love it yeah but but um so I
think what's it's freedom of thought
should be unfettered you can think
whatever you want but when you start to
get into speech where it is can be
spread around and picked up by other
people it's a different animal now what
so the solution I came up with is that
in social media because it has a life of
its own and we can't people should be
able to say what they want they should
also be required to describe their
speech as truthful or not
truthful so if I say um I post on
Facebook oh my dog is the cutest dog in
the world I will also have to say this
is not true this is my opinion right if
I say the election was rigged I have to
say this is not true it's my opinion
right and if some if I say the election
was really it's true anybody can come
back and say nope nope nope all the
evidence shows there is no evidence that
this election was rigged it's not true
and then that person gets warned and if
they keep doing it they get taken off
because it's like nope you're required
to accurately describe your
speech you're still free to speak but
you must accurately describe it because
we're in a world in which the spee can
be the speech can be equally true or
equally false yeah you know it it you
can say both but you have to tell us
which one you're saying so if somebody
says you know Hillary Clinton is a
pedophile I have to say it's false it's
my opinion and then everybody can go oh
that it's their opinion you know
what I mean it's like you at least have
described it as something that is untrue
right you know and that's the best I can
do because people have the right to
speak in our society so that was my
solution uh to and the regulation is
very easy because the guys at the top
the the you know the Zuckerberg's and
the Elon musks they must say you know
they can put in the thing that that says
you have to describe your speech you
can't even post unless you describe it
as true or false you know and that you
take responsibility for this post and
then and then there's two or three rul
rules that say you can argue whether
it's true or argue whether it's false
and then if you do it three times you're
out like fine so yeah that's an idea I I
I I want to put up I am not an expert on
social media but I want to put out
things that say this is actually I said
you know if this is how a cell work a
cell is required to put its information
up to the brain and the brain gets to
decide what it needs to do about the
cell situation so if you cut your finger
there are messages that go up from the
cells to the brain and the Brain says oh
emergency on right index finger you guys
get down there fix it make what happens
first of all you get a clot then you get
a you know then you get a scar and then
it's back to normal you know because
this stuff is going we need we should be
able to do the same thing right and the
thing is if it's a cell a cell's gonna
look at Facebook and go well 99.9% of
this is crap we don't even need this
yeah you know but but people roll
differently people like the 99% you know
stupid stuff on on social media so let
it go we have to be we have to adjust
for humans but nature can guide us in
how to proceed yeah yeah yeah I I was
thinking of um I as much as it's often
just a sess poool but I do drop in from
time to time on Twitter and um they have
a uh Community notes I don't know if
you've seen that and I think that's
that's a I like that I think it's a step
in the right direction for us to landing
on sometimes it's a little confusing
because it's like well who is the
Arbiter of Truth here like is there a
seiling that who who watches The Watcher
sort of there is that whole thing but I
think it's a step in the right direction
well nature requires the every cell to
report up so my thing was well if nature
can make every sell report you make
every poster report on their work don't
make an Arbiter don't you don't have to
have Community codes every person must
report on their own and they are going
to then learn if they don't understand
the difference between a truth and a lie
they're going to figure it out pretty
darn quick yeah and that's the
difference is you make you you put the
responsibility where it is where it is
most effective and this one I think it's
most effective when you make people be
accountable for their actions because a
lot of these people post this stuff and
they're not accountable for how where it
goes and how how far it goes and what
damage they're doing so I'm GNA make
them I want them to be accountable for
what they say and when it comes back
there's going to be somebody says oh
somebody posted this and said it was
true and it is not we can get that guy
to rec you know to post and say oops we
screwed up here or whatever or yeah they
don't get to play because truth is
important knowing that something is true
and knowing that something is false in
our world today is very important very
important we don't have any mechanisms
to do that so this is a very easy one to
make everybody start being trained on
how to know the difference between lie
and Truth yeah yeah I mean I I think
what happens with social media that gets
really confusing is so as much as very
important conversations are taking place
on there there's also like you know
there's also so me laying in bed before
I'm trying to fall asleep just trying to
get a little laugh from a from you know
a fart joke or what something right next
dog video for me yeah yeah yeah it's so
it's it's kind of hard I I I I kind of
just wonder where we're gonna end up you
know in 10 years when we talk about
social media are we going to have this
strange conversation yeah we used to
have all that stuff right on the same
like within a millisecond you're looking
you know you just thought about
something deep about society and the
government and human's existence and
then the next thing is like just you
know a dog part so yeah exactly exactly
and that's the and you know what if
that's what we want to do that's okay
but let's let's put some accountability
there for the things that are again the
problem is you're having just like you
said I would I would reinterpret what
you said as you can have non-harmful
posts and harmful posts and they're all
mixed up together yeah so how do you how
do you let people know what they're
getting right and that's what I'm saying
is that people have to say it themselves
and over time people will get trained oh
I know I'm not going to be able to say
that because it's not true unless I say
it's false and then it's like okay you
know you said the election was rigged
but that's false I'll just put it out
there as false you know right right like
people FMA didn't come to Asheville it's
like actually they did so you have to
say h just my opinion it's like well
what do you know you live in Minnesota
you know yeah yeah yeah yeah I me I
think that is a powerful move though is
is putting the responsibility on
that's we should be deeply we're
interacting with each other in in
potentially a very profound way we
should take responsibility I do kind of
Wonder um about I spent a lot of time in
the world of uh just creating stuff I
like write a lot of poetry um I make a
lot of music I'm really not very good at
making music but I love making it um
sometimes I like sharing you know just I
mean sometimes I'm going on a walk and I
smoked a joint and I want to share a
thought so right I I get like sometimes
having all that freedom exist in the
same place like sometimes I'm hard it's
hard to quantify right that right well
again what you're saying is exactly the
nature of humans is we want to maximize
our freedom and I'm like all for
maximizing Freedom yeah but the only
line is no harm to others if you went on
your walk you smoked a joint and you
punched somebody out you P you cross the
line right but if you go and you do it
and you're thinking your thoughts and
you're maybe making up some new music
that's great that's what I want people
to do the world is great when everybody
is in tune with what their values are
and doing them that's what makes the
world great and if everybody could just
let everybody do that and not be afraid
that they're gonna get hurt by the next
guy who doesn't like how they look yeah
you
know we have to that's to me if you're
going to make a better world you have to
Envision a better world first and that's
what I'm doing here is envisioning the
the core the goal or the the foundation
of a better world and then lots of
people fill in the gaps
yeah yeah yeah brilliant I love that um
okay so where where do you see the
concepts that you that you've posed in
not just this book um and this is the
only one that I've read from you but
along with your other books uh for one I
would love to know kind of what's what's
what seems to be for you anyway the kind
of the through line between them them if
any um and also what do
you what are your expectations with this
work like what what sorts of you know
outside of of these conversations like
do you want to be cross laterally uh
collaborating with with other
philosophers and and scientists who are
also in these same worlds like like
where would you like this to end up or
do you want it to face okay um has a
good question so I'll start with the
through line of the books and then I'll
tell you what I um remind me if I forget
to tell you what I'd want to you know
where I want this to be but so I started
writing books I only write books when I
have something to say something
important to say and my first book is
about happiness um and it was my
struggle because I grew up really
insecure of the 11th of 12 children and
a pretty you know an anxiously you know
um designed person it was hard I had a
lot of I just had a lot of trouble when
I was early on and so this is a like
little vignette of my challenges and
like little lessons I learned from them
and what I but what I came down to in
this book was that I needed to make my
own values but that was it when later on
the book about humans need to make their
own goals I had discovered independently
sort of for my own sanity that I had to
do that yeah so it ends up being oh no
that's the actually kind of a based on
how this all works we really need to do
that because that's a whole that Miss in
how we designed you know so that was
that one the second book is kind of a
romantic suspense Business book and it
was really starting my views about
business and what you know that that I
have a big section in my book about the
dangers of profit maximization right
that profit maximization is a vehicle by
which people um can harm others and say
well I got a good reason I maximize my
profits agree and and it also skews the
resources into One Direction because
once you get really good and get a lot
of resources you can use those resources
to um to change your environment you can
buy off the government you know you can
Lobby Lobby the government legally that
is just legalized bribery you know and
do all these things so so I have a I'm
accountant and I have economic
background but profit maximization is to
me one of the great evils of of a
society uh of coexistence and living
together it's what creates social
inequality and creates so many pressures
on people when we should be going the
other way um so that book was sort of my
start of that and it was a it was just a
fiction it it's a love story and it's
all that stuff but that's what that one
is and then Dena was where this one
where I worked out the theory using the
socratic dialogue between the the
creatures you know that Sarah and and
Dena and that was where I really worked
out the details of how this worked and
it's twice as long as the theory book
and the theory book the human idea which
is this new one it just came out this
one I just cut the story out and put in
more examples and it's just the theory
so that's how they all link together but
those early books were really seeds
planting seeds this was the thing I been
thinking about this stuff I hadn't put
it together yet and this is just the
culmination of putting those ideas
together in one place so and so what I
want out of this is I want to be a
Charles Darwin who's
alive you know I want to be the the
person who sort of is the you can go to
and say oh Ann Riley created IDE ideas
for the but look at what we can do with
it I don't really care about an Riley
that's just the base but look what we
can do with this idea and that's what I
really want is I want it to spread as
far and wide is because there are so
many smarter people than me who know so
much more than me and if they applied
this one concept what would their
decisions look like what would
homelessness look like what would
education look like what would policing
look like what would you know these
militaristic groups look like how do we
do this I have ideas on all of those
based on just this Simple Start and I'm
not an expert in any of them but part of
that is my advantage because I'm not I'm
not bogged down by the details they know
but if they could tell what I knew and
then say Oh but here are the details
they can figure out how to make them
work yeah I can't you see what I mean
that's what I want for the
future yeah
I love that I think that's so good I I
umum uh yeah it makes me think you might
you may have heard this but um uh this
concept that I think you'll like that
I've heard is uh being the Usher of
epiphany yeah what do you think about
that that that's a pretty high standard
setting the ideas out like it comes to
you and you're making sure it goes out
but like it's not necessarily a personal
like I need to achieve this thing don't
want in fact you know I'm old the and
the world's going to go on
you know I want I want this to be an
idea that people Embrace because it's a
good idea not because it's my idea that
will probably go the other way I like oh
it's her idea uhuh you know but I'm like
you know I want people to say oh yeah
there's some value here and I can use
this and make the world a better place
but from what I'm talking about we need
a we have a long way to go we do not
make decisions this way we have not
structured our econ economy our social
structures our anything this way we got
a long way to go but if you start it may
only be a few Generations before the
world would really be a better place
yeah absolutely yeah yeah let's at least
get the right hand talking to the left
hand you know exactly exactly exactly
yeah well um cool let me glance to my
notes over here just make sure there
wasn't any I I I had so many I just uh
your book was difficult toight as I I
was reading it I feel like every three
sentences I have like oh that Sparks a
cool idea and I had to write it down and
after a while I had to chill out on
taking my own notes because I wasn't
getting anywhere on the book so yeah
well and that that's why the book is so
important is it has everything in there
in like a small space right there are I
say to people I say you don't understand
there's a lot in there what do you maybe
there's one part you might want to talk
about because if you just want to talk
about all of it there's a lot yeah yeah
yeah you know but that's why you write a
book like this if you read Darwin's
Origin species he goes through
all his case he makes he not only does
he make the case for he takes every
argument against Evolution and he bats
it down and I was just he was the
smartest person in history in in my
opinion because he was just he was a
thinker he could just think through it
all and I used him as a guide you know
to help me reason through this you know
but but um there's a lot in there and
you know every chapter has something
that oh oh oh you know and I want you to
feel that way I want you to keep reading
but the thing is is if you start I
started a big bang and I end up at you
know the structure of government you
would that's a long way to go you know
yeah yeah you did it pretty elegantly to
be honest yeah I I I do feel like it's a
very inviting for someone like I was
saying earlier for someone who isn't
typically in these Realms of like
studying or thinking deeply about this
stuff it's super inviting it lays out
these things that for the most part A
lot of people you know we kind of
learned at least a good percentage of a
lot of the stuff that you said you know
in school and college and whatnot it's
it's it's very easy to as I'm listening
to the book go like yeah makes complete
sense yeah I agree couldn't agree more
and so it does stack on itself nicely
yeah I I did have a lot of people say
yeah I reviewed high school biology you
know and I was like yeah but then
there's sociology and then there's
economics and then but then you end up
in a different place for people and
that's what I wanted I wanted you I
wanted my reader to see the through line
between nature
and human the the construction of a
human society and it you know I am a
step-by-step thinker so I had to do it
step by step yeah yeah well it helps
other people other people wrap their
head around it so it's not so daunting
so sometimes I feel like um I use the I
use the term throwing out the baby with
the bath water I use it just way too
much so sorry for listeners who have
sick of hearing me hear it say it but um
I I do think that I mean I I stumbled
into kind of the world of understanding
myself and humans and um like not only
just my own thought process but like
what you know what does it mean to be a
human the whole why are we here just the
you know everybody has those moments in
their life I mean I stumbled on to it uh
via necessity and so I I felt that I
dealt with a lot of depression and these
sorts of things I was confused about who
I was and what I should do blah blah
blah make lying to myself not realizing
I was lying to myself and experiencing
the rep I think I'm I'm in that club too
so yeah oh you're human as well gotcha
yeah I got it yeah yeah um and so I'm
just always
like back to the throw throwing the baby
out with the bathwater is is I realized
as much as I was so egotistically sure
that I already kind of knew everything I
needed to know um like all these old
these old texts and stuff are hippie
dippy and and I don't really need to
indulge myself in the way other people
think to understand myself blah blah
blah um but I I do think that
so important that everybody even outside
of necessity and outside of being forced
to because your brain is attacking you
out of depression whatever it's such a
superpower to understand yourself on
like such a deep level um
and I don't know I I I don't I guess
suppose I don't have a question for you
on that and but what do you think about
that does that make you think of
anything there well and I think it's so
I think you're right I think that the
well um that was sort of the point of my
first book was I couldn't be happy until
I think the okay spoiler on this book
sorry readers don't listen if you don't
want to hear this but there's five words
um in order for me to be happy identify
your values live them that's it and so
what happened is once I did that I
became at home with me when you become
at home with yourself you can figure out
how to become at home with the world and
that's what I did
and it's just been a learning experience
I have to keep like you I don't know
everything I have to keep learning then
the job I have is to keep my eyes and
ears open and be like um maybe I'm not
getting something here let's work on
that you know but you start the core is
there so you don't beat yourself up
because you're not perfect of course
you're not perfect you're a human
nothing's perfect but you can be the
best you can be and that's all you need
to be is the best of you and then you
give yourself out in the world the way
you want to and you're much more
comfortable because your AA is hey I'm
cool with me and people love be being
around people who are cool with
themselves because they just get it it's
a it's an unspoken thing they'll be like
oh I kind of like that I kind of like
that so I think the young kids call it
Riz or something now dud yeah yeah but
it's it doesn't have to be it's just
gonna be R you know what I mean you can
just be okay yourself yeah
exactly but uh so so what are the uh uh
one more time what were the five words
identify your values live them that's
profound what what are the benefits I'm
sure you say this in the book what are
the benefits of identifying your your
values that was another thing in that
same rambling that I had it was I didn't
realize I didn't even know my own values
I was like values I never really thought
that deeply about that and it was a
whole thing unfolded for me so right
it's it
um it you know values are equivalent to
goals and when you have DNA member human
born with no goals no born with no ideas
they can't have goals and they can't
have values they have to establish their
own animals don't need to they don't
need them they got their instructions
they go they they come out born
perfectly capable of living as a a horse
or a tiger in the world we are not born
perfectly capable to live as humans in
the world we have to learn stuff and
what we learn is dependent on what other
people learn before us so when I say
identify values it means you have to
learn your own goals from all the things
you learned and all the things you read
and done all these things you have to
say this is what works for me and the
only way you know is you feel this sort
of inside that says yeah that's the one
for me so for me personally I came out
my values aren't external um like like I
will feel better if I have a million
dollar house or something like that it's
like well just go to California you know
it's easy you know but um but for me the
the values that I came up with with the
word heck honesty empathy calm and kind
those are the four values that work for
me and sometimes I don't do them and
then I'm like come on back you need to
practice some more but if I do those I
tend to be at home with myself and
everybody has a different set of
whatever it could be it could be
anything it just depends on what
connects to you and this is the whole
idea people choose because they have to
be able to choose what works for them so
maximizing choice and giving people to
understand that they get to make the
choices for that are right for them is
what will make them happy you know it
all connects to in my mind it all
connects together yeah yeah no it
totally does I uh um uh it makes me
think of um oh my gosh I get excited
sometimes and then I lose the thought
but uh um I was thinking about
um oh dang it I lost it okay it it was
something uh apparently not worthwhile
in that moment um but I I I will say um
I I did I feel like I'm going to uh
replicate what you have behind you in
some way I feel like I I also do little
sticky notes so yeah I do sticky notes
because I'm an apartment now I can't
necessarily ride on the wall but my
house back originally from Washington
State I used to write I notic the 360
number where in Washington uh I grew up
just north of Portland Oregon about an
hour north so Kelso Washington is the
name oh Kelo yeah I lived in Portland
for 35 years and I was born in in
Richland so other side of the state
Richland Washington so yeah I saw the
360 number and I said I wonder if you're
still there yeah no I I I not I found my
way down to Austin uh about five years
ago I I work in the event industry and
so the pic pmic really like just set me
for a loop so I just had to escape to
somewhere that was open so um I've been
in awesome five years but I'm I'm I'm
definitely missing the Pacific Northwest
tons so yeah well now I'm in the midwest
because we were uh we spent the last 10
years caring for elderly parents so but
um you know I think we're making our way
back West we have two of our kids are
back there so we'll probably make it
make our way back there so yeah I love
the West it just more suits me a little
bit better but yeah I think I'm with you
on that yeah yeah but it's it's
beautiful though because the way life
works is uh I've been here about five
years like I said I'm starting to take a
step back and go kind of ask myself why
I'm here and and why I ended up here and
what it's done but I look you know
things like in my work and my just
personal development of me as a person
is I go I see why I moved here I see why
I needed to move here and develop these
parts of my you know just personal
structure and how I express myself I I
needed this this few years of this in my
life regardless of where I end up um I I
see value right right and that's the
thing is nature is nothing but change
and so what works for you now and works
for you may change over time and as long
as open to it and say oo I think I'm
ready for something different you know
what what is it that I'm still looking
for what is it that I want to accomplish
or what am I missing those are things
that only you can tell yourself because
you're your own expert no one else can
tell you and you you don't have to have
you don't have to make decision you can
run over all kinds of ideas because
ideas are free you can have as many of
them as you want and then but acting on
them you have to be a little more
judicious and so play with the ideas and
then you know poke around and and what
you act on is where that will impact you
because it starts go it's a thing in the
world right it exists in the world when
you move from Austin to Tennessee you
know it's a change in the world that's
going to affect everything so those you
want to be really judicious about but
ideas ah go at them have as many as you
want look at them from different
perspectives you know that's great
because they don't exist they don't
exist in the real world they just exist
in your mind and that's okay yeah yeah
that's brilliant that's fascinating um
while we are getting up here in time I
think that's a pretty decent note to uh
start pointing us towards um what what I
want to do so obviously in the in the
description I'll have some links to to
your books and where to find more info
about you but also just for anybody
who's still listening in this moment
right now um what what are you working
on next how do they connect with you how
do they explore more of your stuff if
they're if they're turned on by what
we've been talking about right well
right now I the the the newest book just
came out two weeks ago and I was in the
midst of all this stuff with my mom so
I've done literally no not very much on
that so but you know on the other hand
I'm like I guess I like the person who
took care of her mom rather than worried
about her book you know I guess I like
that person better so I'm good you but
but I think ultimately I do want to put
together my ideas about the current
problems of today using this mindset um
as a book that maybe could get people
started you know to say let's talk about
homelessness what would nature do well
nature doesn't even have homeless cells
you know a cell lives in a body and it
is always fed it's always taken care of
it has to tow its line 247 and it you
know if it it has to report up how it's
doing so given that how would we treat
homelessness you know how would we treat
like I said education how would we treat
police violence what a great Baseline
yeah yeah exactly it's a way to think
and that base of thinking will make will
really Drive different kinds of
decisions and the question for me is to
Envision them enough for somebody else
to say oh you might be able to do that
that's what I want so that's probably
the next thing I'll work on you know um
and I just don't know when I'll start
that it's runs around in my head but and
you know what I think the last time I
was like oh this will take oh a couple
months to write five years later still
going you
know so I don't know because I Leave
Myself open to that that's the point for
me I always have to leave my mind open I
don't have any strict rules about what
what I should do or what has to be done
because part of my mind always has to
remain open to the new ideas that are
coming in yeah I find myself I get I get
in my own way if I end up trying to
structure it too much and trying to plan
it too much I end up like tripping over
my own dang feet if I do that too much
so yeah well and I know that I'm not the
smartest person in the world so I need
input from people and I read something I
go oh that that's a good idea I I did a
podcast with a lady talking about plant
intelligence and it was really
interesting and and what what we got out
of that is that by humans having their
brain they're literally Less close to
Nature because we have to filter it
through this thinking process whereas
plants and animals are just directly
linked to Nature yeah you know and
plants even more so because they don't
have even brains they they have this
neural system but not really a brain I
was like oh you're right they can just
respond to Nature like this and we like
have to go wait I have to think about
that and what am I going to do and I
have to build a structure and I have to
no I was like oh and her she titled it
how brains limit us and I was like wow I
never even thought of that so that's a
nice title too yeah I I just totally
totally blew me away that oh I had even
all this stuff I'm talking about humans
and it's like kind of as they're so
unique and interesting and it's like
actually maybe they're not as great as
we thought yeah yeah I've been I've been
slowly chipping away at this book called
uh light eaters it's like it's about
plants and and um like the life behind
plants it's so fascinating the author is
really good too um right but it's funny
that you mentioned that because I I was
actually GNA try to bring that that same
book into this conversation earlier
because I was wondering what what you
would think about it so maybe check that
one out it's called light eaters light
eaters I will I will well um This
Woman's name who did the podcast with me
her name is
gardinia uh and it's Tiger Lily gardinia
I was like well that's a good name for a
plant person
but she had several she if you ever look
her up she's I think she's on podcast
that's where I found or pod match that's
where I found her nice um she might be
interesting to talk to you because you
might get some really especially if
you're reading this other book she she's
fascinating you know yeah I've been my
mind has been being blown like little
facts they they were talking about how
they would take a speaker underground or
some sort of in some sort of environment
and they would play the sound of running
water and then they would notice that oh
The Roots will intentionally listen
somehow hear the sound of the running
water and go towards it and move that
way yeah yeah and that makes me have to
like take a break from the rest of my
day it's so profound to me so cool the
implications of that yeah and this is
what I what I assume is that there
are abilities that plants and animals
have that we have no way with our five
senses to understand and we just don't
and so rather than I mean I can't even
imagine that that we can see them as
inferior beings they are different
beings and their skills or their
abilities are so different that we
should stop and and and and before we do
some of the horrible things we do to
animals we should stop and think about
things because there are there there's
just mystery out there that we don't
know stuff we don't know I call it
energy energy we don't know and it moves
ways we can't even fathom and rather
than you know this whole concept of
manifest destiny and we're the kings of
the world I'm no we are participants in
a big web yeah and we should be
respectful of that yeah it's a pretty
bold claim to think that we're like the
the the head of it the only ones who who
have it all figured out yeah but that
claim started thousands years ago and
we've decided a big number of us have
decided to keep that claim going so even
though if you look around you're like ah
facts don't bear that out but yeah yeah
it's a in that book uh uh they I think
they talk about how um uh we they talk
about Consciousness basically in in kind
of the assumption that we kind of always
assumed that a brain is what gives rise
to Consciousness like it requires like a
complex synapsis firing thing but then
uh we're kind of discovering that okay
like this plant is clearly so
intelligent in a way that is a Beyond a
brain in this in some crazy yeah
separate it has a neural system that
manag to do all that without needing and
probably
because um you know every neural system
grows within the environment that can
support it so there are I mean plants
have been around they're the winners in
the evolutionary I mean there's 450 you
know
I mean uh gigum Mass bites whatever they
call it but they're the winners I mean
they're 80% of all life in in carbon
mass as plants but but animals need
brains because they move you know they
have to move they have to maneuver in
the world they have to they have to
figure themselves out there's a lot more
brain power needed to do that than it is
for an animal with or a plant with roots
in the ground but the plant still does
all the other things that it needs to do
to survive it works with the other
plants it it protects itself it does all
the other things it just doesn't need a
big brain to do it it's just very
efficient you know but we don't we I
mean that still is kind of an a far out
everybody goes oh yeah what are you
smoking today to have come up with the
plan intelligence concept like no just
yeah exactly yes yeah those what they
told me yeah yeah yeah yeah weed gave me
this idea directly yeah exactly it was
like hey stupid you know but uh you know
that's that's the thing is um I have a a
quote up on my wall it's by kaes John
Mayor kanes it says the difficulty lies
not so much in developing new ideas as
in escaping from old ones and I think
that is where we are in this world today
there's a lot of ideas that we need to
escape from before we can come up with
the new ones absolutely yeah yeah well
well said I love your choice of course
also by the way we both have Albert
Einstein right behind our heads third I
have a lot of his quotes this one's good
one the other one is and one I live by
is make things as simple as possible but
never
simpler and I love that one too and that
was the what I used to write this book
it was this is as simple as I could make
it but sometimes I couldn't go simpler
because it just wasn't gonna I wasn't
GNA tell you the I wasn't G to tell you
what you need to know yeah so yeah I I
the word I I remember thinking of the
word concise I've been using that word a
lot in my own mental things and I as I'm
listening to your to your uh book
thinking of word concise you did such a
great job on that you also just just
around all the the plant talk I I took
us on a little side side quest on the
end um I was G you you talk about it
made me even think about more things you
know you present uh words like ecosystem
really really elegantly um I love the
way you describe all that so if anybody
has been enticed at all who's who's
listening right now like uh an expands
on a lot of this stuff that it's like
there's a lot of touching billiard balls
uh so so yeah there there's
a your book is is worthwhile and it's
enjoyable and um yeah thank you so much
for writing it everybody check it out we
are getting up here in time I I don't
want to hold you off too long in um but
so thank you so much I really appreciate
your time thank you for writing this
thank you for willing to send it to me
and spend some time with me today and
let me I loved it I had such a
delightful time you are very great
conversation list good questions good
conversation just and you make me think
a lot so I love that it's my favorite
thing to do is think so likewise yeah I
I man okay well The Light in Me seas and
honors a light in you and thank you for
following following this internal thing
and writing this book and and doing all
this so um I'll be in touch everybody
else check out Ann stuff the links are
below and Ann you have a good rest of
your day okay and you too thank you so
much this was really really really
enjoyable likewise yeah
we okay bye
[Music]
knowledge is
power reality is
[Music]
junkyard love podcast